hello it's February 22nd 2023 we're in
meeting five
four cohort three
we're in our second discussion on
chapter two
today we'll be mostly looking at
questions from chapter two carrying
people's like thoughts on it
written or whatever they want to bring
up today and then in the last few
minutes we'll look ahead to chapter
three
first though wanted to note underneath
live meetings
on February 27th in five days we will
have Thomas Parr join for a live stream
first author so it's at 17 UTC
um for likely an hour
if anybody wants to join the live stream
itself
then just email activeinference Gmail
and let us know and we'll add you to the
calendar event
if you want to watch along live here's
the or share it and this is like the
watch and the re-watch link
and then if you have any specific
questions
it could be something that we've already
raised
or it could be something more General
slash personal
so just before we jump to chapter two
what does anyone think would be
interesting or meaningful to ask Thomas
feel free to think about it or type it
um here but basically when
the day comes it's going to be whoever
has um thank you Jonathan it's going to
be whoever is there in the moment
so just email if you want to join on
that stream
and whichever questions are here
slash questions that we've just curated
and then if there's time or if anyone is
watching live they can put a question in
the live chat too
so
um
we'll continue to explore like what
kinds of engagements with Thomas Gianni
and Carl
are best for the book and everything but
this is going to be a lot of fun
okay
well we have many chapter two questions
does anyone have a specific one they
wanna
jump into first or just any
chapter two
reflection or a comment that they want
to share there's totally time to do that
if you want to
foreign
[Music]
comments and questions
kind of just drawing
draw from the question posterior
how does active inference go beyond the
recognition that action and perception
have the same inferential nature
page 24.
what do people think so
this is probably referring to section
2.4
um how do we go beyond
recognizing well
maybe perception and learning have a
similar inferential nature maybe we can
have a unified framework that models
perception and action together and maybe
they even have a unified imperative
I think the simplest answer is they're
different parameters
that's how we move past that recognition
they're modeled as different parameters
in a unified model
so you want to add another thought or
question on that
foreign
specific question to go to otherwise we
have many that we can
come to
okay
why Express
potential energy and expected free
energy in the space of log probabilities
on page 33. consistent with the notion
of potential energy and physics expected
free energy is expressed in the space of
log probabilities
nice question any first thoughts let's
look at where it was
in the textbook
so we're talking about taking the
expected free energy of each policy
so equation 2.6
expected free energy over policies
that's sharpening our action prior our
habits into the action posterior that
we're actually going to sample our
actions from
does anyone want to give a thought on
that question
yeah so um
in one of my maths modules we're
currently studying Bayesian maths and um
one of the benefits of using
probabilities is to make it easier to
calculate derivatives when you're
modeling gaussians and a second point
was like computational benefit you might
encounter floating Point errors when
dealing with I think marginal evidence
which can be very small for some values
so calculating the log version of those
um reduces the likelihood of getting
encountering inflation Point issues and
precision errors that's what I'm trying
to say
awesome thank you
yeah the log is something that's like
very simple whether it's like log base 2
or Ln the natural log
it it does a lot and it also has one
foot
in the kind of computational
tractability benefits
like being able to keep track of small
probabilities like if you have a hundred
options that most of them are going to
be small like less than one percent now
if you have a thousand options most of
them are going to be small like on
average less than a tenth of a percent
so as you get many options or
probability distributions you want to be
able to keep track with high resolution
of these very small numbers on real
computers so it helps purely
pragmatically in
the kinds of computers we have today
then a little bit more mathematically
the log connects to Jensen's inequality
and also to um
information Theory and self-suprisal
and then something that's unpacked a lot
more in Bayesian physics and less in
this textbook itself
is like physics uses kind of like
gravity as like a self-information
not exactly you know read where it's
actually connected
but it turns out that like the ball
rolling to the bottom of the hill to
minimize the potential energy
has a lot to do with the quote ball
rolling to the bottom of the hill of a
statistical distribution if we think
about self-surprise self-information
in a log probability space Ollie
yes and uh one more advantage of using a
lot of probabilities is uh to order uh
more generally to use logs instead of
the actual parameters is
um to convert some of the
multiplications to addition and hence uh
trying to convert at least parts of the
non-linearities of the equations to
linear equations so
in that case well of course we know
dealing with linear equations
is much more tractable and also much
more
[Applause]
I mean linear techniques has much more
developed than just dealing with
directly with nonlinear equations and
nonlinear capillations
thanks yeah two of the log properties
that come into play a lot
and you can go back and forth like
they're used in both directions
here log of M times m so log of 5 times
10 log of 50. equals log of 5 plus log
of 10. so you can break multiplication
inside of the parentheses you can break
it into two Logs with the same a value
and analogously if you have like log M
minus log n it's the same as log of
M divided by n
and these kinds of Maneuvers and
rewritings
are used greatly
and it turns out that the KL Divergence
which is one Divergence measure that's
used so just like you'll know that
you're doing you're doing better in the
least
um squares sum of squares linear
regression world you know that you're
doing better when the sum of squares is
going down
in the KL Divergence World variational
inference World your model is getting
better fit when the KL Divergence is
going down
again there's more detail but these all
are empowered by the ability to
have something within a log
that's multiplied
which also gives this the interpretation
as like potentially a self-suprisal
self-information
and then separate that out and do
addition
so it has computational benefits
it has statistical benefits and it has
also a deeper connection to Bayesian
physics
foreign
okay Ollie go for it
uh sorry before going into the next
question I just wanted to comment on the
previous question the question number
two uh sorry I erased my hand a little
bit uh later so uh you didn't notice but
uh yeah about the relation between the
perception and action uh so very briefly
uh Alan bertho's
um actually proposes that uh perception
is uh simulated action so it basically
implies that perception and motion are
kind of
irreducibly interconnected and actually
he also claims that the former I mean
the perception defines the action so
yeah it's uh also uh another Viewpoint
which is uh way before uh the
development of active inference and
um pre-energy principle but these ideas
of the interconnection between the
action and perception uh has been uh
discussed uh all I mean throughout the
history of cognitive science and
especially uh the last few decades in
terms of embodied cognition and so on
but in my view Alan berthoud's uh Claim
about this specific interconnection
between perception and action and
basically uh making them equivalent uh
in to each other uh in terms of their
um one of which being the simulation of
the other is an interesting Viewpoint to
have in mind beyond the inferential
nature of them
nice yeah like even qualitatively
we can draw connections with different
threads like helmholtz perception is
unconscious inference okay now just save
that thank you for the thing okay now
what's the pragmatic turn
well that's about in the Bayesian brain
it's about thinking about action
alongside inference so it's like okay we
have helmholtz perception is unconscious
inference
now let's extend that to action and
perception as unconscious inference
that's still a qualitative idea
and octave and fep are helping us
develop quantitative methods
that
are compatible
with with those kind of qualitative ways
of thinking about perception cognition
and action
okay upper bound I think we came to last
week so
what is meant by bounded computational
and mnemonic resources
anyone have a thought on this or related
idea
I think this is great
answer just
you can write an equation you know 10 to
the 10 to the 10 to the 10 to the 10 to
the 10 to the 10th power
but just because you can write it on a
piece of paper doesn't mean that there's
like a calculator that has that much RAM
am I just you know the number of digits
that you need to store might be outside
of
the heat capacity of Earth or something
like that so
we want to be able to express models in
an open-ended way
in principle
also
especially if we're talking about what
kind of inference is optimal
it's important to take this probably
approximately correct
approximate Bayesian computation
heuristics
angle
that respects the actual
time space
trade-offs that are
fundamental for any actual
system
and any model that we make of a given
like
it's not behaving accurately and you
know
if it remembered every single Pixel
it's like well yeah but there's not
enough space for it to remember every
pixel so it might be doing something
that's actually very adaptive involving
forgetting the vast majority of
information
and there's there's no trade-off there
but if we can only state the models in
principle
and we don't keep it bounded with the um
limitations of real systems
and the approximate Bayesian computation
framework then
you know
maybe the scripts don't run because and
and that's also really yeah there's
other angles there any thoughts or
comments on this or this is a good
answer
also kind of a nice
link to
um mnemonic resources
like Memory Palace
like what if you didn't have to remember
every single word in the poem but you
remembered some nested model
where the higher part of the nested
model involved
touching parts of the environment or
walking through an imagined space
are the cognitive
constraints or challenges associated
with those types of mnemonic resources
that cue
one's action
does that have some properties that are
beneficial
relative to kind of like
the naked memory
how does active inference
incorporate feelings into the framework
theory in the Apple frog example when
the human believes she is confronted
with an apple before the observation is
she feeling hungry or low on glucose
when she subsequently observes the thing
jump does that observation include the
feeling of disappointment the release of
stress hormones Etc
what would anyone say on this
Jonathan and then anyone else
yeah so I I wrote the the thing below
that that I I think that there's a
strong relationship there between
feelings and observations
um in the in the sense that we observe
our bodily States but I think this ties
in nicely with um some of Mark Sultan's
um work on on affect and Consciousness
um
yeah so I think that yeah one once you
think about bodily States and the
inferences we make about the state that
we're in based on those observations
nice thank you anyone else
I would put this in the county oh yeah
I'll leave first go for it
uh yeah I just wanted to point out that
there's actually a theory of emotions or
feelings developed with inactive uh
active inference framework and we deeply
felt affect uh Theory uh developed by uh
Casper hesp and Ryan Smith and others uh
so uh
if anyone's interested in exploring how
active how we can theoretically frame
feelings uh purely in terms of active
imprints I would highly recommend
reading this fascinating paper
from I guess to 2020.
yes thank you
I would put it in the category of
possible to model like you could make a
model about it you could write a paper
about it
but not intrinsic Within
the simplest kernel
because feelings also as Psalms will
um be
um
Keen to point out feelings implies a
feeler
and so that is bringing in the qualia
phenomenology experience awareness
topic
but the model can also be stated
without those
considerations playing an outsized role
but if someone's making a map like a
generative model
and they want to include those variables
there are some strategies that people
have been implementing for years
to engage with affective States
in a computational psychiatry
approach
like and just an empirical strategy
might be like we start with a simple
model
and then we find oh there's like this
interesting residual pattern where
people are
um overestimating How likely apples are
around noon
and then we get a new sensor in our
laboratory now we're measuring glucose
or we um are getting some Health Data so
now we can differentiate people who have
this metabolic condition from that and
we're finding that they have a different
inference strategy
so it's not about just sketching it and
just saying oh it's a done deal because
it's on paper it's about that iterative
modeling
and a plurality of possible ways that
feelings
could be implemented
though I think Psalms and others will
say that they have
um in silico
feeling agents
so that again opens up a whole other
level of discussion
all right
when quantifying dissimilarity between
the prior and posterior
so for example Bayesian surprise so
surprise alone just surprisal
is about one data point coming in how
surprised are we
measured in information theoretic units
like a not or a bit
but if we're talking about Bayesian
surprise we're talking about how much
the prior shifts to become the posterior
as a function of the observation coming
in why do we choose the KL Divergence
over other measures
is it just a canonical Choice does it
matter since KL Divergence is asymmetric
is there any reason we have chosen this
particular order is there any intuition
motivating the choice does anyone want
to give a first thought
okay one example of an alternative
measure here's with um Sajid
at all
foreign
this is getting
um
kind of as far as we might want to visit
it here but
it's important that the kale diversions
as the questioner notes it's not
actually a measure
in the proper
metric sense and I mean like European
metric system
like if it the measurement between A and
B has to be the same between b and a for
it to be a distance measure
um whereas the KL Divergence it is a
quantitative value but the Divergence
from A to B is not necessarily B to a in
fact it's generally not so
KL Divergence is an asymmetric
Divergence quantification
now it's possible to have a very closely
related Divergence called the Jeffries
which is just the KL Plus
the other direction
so it calculates like it's basically the
KL of a to B plus the KL of B to a and
so that is symmetric hence that is a
real distance measure
um other measures have been proposed the
rainy
and they may discuss other options as
well
um why is it used
in the context of variational Bayesian
inference and probability it just turns
out that the log properties work and um
in
equate one of the earlier equations
which maybe Ali will remember
specifically like
a illegal for it and I'll think about
which equation is the one with the KL
definition
uh it was equation 2.3 and uh yeah uh
but also uh there is a Lemma called
neyman Pearson Lemma which actually
proves that the most efficient way to
distinguish between two probability
distribution based on a given
observation is a KL Divergence so it's
not just an arbitrary choice but I
believe it's a proven theorem uh I mean
it's the most efficient method for
comparing those two probability
distributions
thank you
also just to kind of give one one
related angle to connect like why this
whole discussion matters for those who
saw that
as in the weeds it definitely is
um the way that that
um pragmatic value
is going to be determined
is ultimately through something kale is
used for information and on the
pragmatic side
but this is how when we talk about
expectation and preference
and we want to evaluate policies based
upon how well they align with our
preferences
that is going to be operationalized by
reducing a KL Divergence
between our preferences and observations
and that
task of optimization
of the incremental reduction of
Divergence relative to our generative
model of incoming observations
that's what we want to solve and it also
turns out to have some good
computational properties
so
Jonathan
yeah I was just going to say just in
terms of the
um the equation that sorry excuse me for
the expected free energy
um I although I I feel very comfortable
in general with with mathematics and
physics
um I I find it very hard to get
intuition from that equation I think it
would be useful maybe it's something
that I'm going to do but to actually run
through a sort of really concrete
example at that stage you know with
numbers so you can see how the two terms
differ for a particular example I think
that would be quite enlightening for for
me to to go through at some stage
thanks I know
some may have notebooks that do that we
have so however people want to share
that or build that that sounds good
um
many ways to go like
but great questions
thank you for who's sharing these
so KL plays nicely with logs
in in the sense that it's defined
essentially in terms of
um the the Divergence between Q to p
again not the distance between q and P
the Divergence between Q to p
is defined as triangle equals
expectation over the variational
Distribution on hidden States so over
the map not over the territory
expectations over the map so the center
of gravity
of our Maps inference on hidden States
of the difference
between
the log
Q of X and P of x
the log again connects us to all of
those nice mathematical computational
statistical properties of logs
and
um
has this Divergence interpretation to
expectation of a difference of logs is a
KL Divergence
and the reason why it's not symmetric is
because
um
P to Q
would be flipped and so it'd be a
different number
unless they were literally both zero
okay
under some conditions one can reduce
variational free energy to other Notions
which conditions
here they're showing it for expected
free energy
these kinds of special reduction
conditions
or special cases
and something analogous can be
um kind of
proposed for variational free energy
it's just not directly shown there
so
um
coming from so in variational free
energy F Q and Y
expected free energy
epistemic value pragmatic value in the
special cases are when for example
pragmatic value which here is shown as
the first term
and then here epistemic value is the
second term
so where
section one is zero this term is just
zeroed out
there's no preferences
preferences are flat all outcomes are
equally pragmatically valuable
then
we only have elements two three four
five and play
that is equivalent to Bayesian surprise
novelty search
optimal Information Gain
in contrast if we had discarded two two
three four five because it's a fully
discovered fully known situation there's
no epistemic value to harvest
then we only have
the left term one which is
classical pragmatic decision Theory
and so on
by acting on the World to Change the way
in which data are generated
we can ensure model is fit for purpose
by choosing those data which are least
surprising under our model
is active inference the process that can
explain treatment resistance
I can kind of imagine what that is but
if somebody who wrote that wants to
describe like what treatment resistance
is
okay under just this first pass
understanding that
um treatment resistance
let's just copy this information in
has to do with um recalcitrance or
resilience
to a given therapeutic intervention
there might be different ways to frame
it
but um if there's a model with a low
learning rate
I am the kind of person who does this
action
then from the clinician's perspective
various interventions
might be characterized the person may be
characterized as resistant to those
interventions because the interventions
are not updating
some aspect of their generative model
so
is it the process can explain treatment
resistance well again that's like asking
is linear regression the process that
can explain the relationship between
heart disease and cancer it's like
I don't know if you write the paper and
the community of experts use it then
it's a going scientific explanation
is just putting these words down the
explanation no
what else needs to be built how can that
question be modeled and engaged with but
does the framework itself simply explain
it no could you explain it and attempt
to build a model that provides unique
Expeditions predictions and control
options I believe so
any comments or questions on this
okay can someone read Bay's rule for me
once again in plain English equation 2.1
now taking into consideration that quote
Bayesian inference minimizes surprisal
surprise
is equivalent to maximizing Bayesian
model evidence
and then they're suggesting that this is
Computing the posterior
any thought on this
equation 2.1
maybe if anyone wants to
type it out in the coming weeks just I I
I'm not 100 sure
but
if you have the model that's
parameterized tuned such that Bayesian
model evidence is maximized
you have found the most likely parameter
the maximum likelihood estimate
for a given sequences of actions given
your priors
so you have the the most
supported model
that is equivalent to saying that with
your most supported model
you've minimized your surprise
so how you read different terms and like
which one you see as kind of upstream or
feeding into the other one
depends on the structure of what your
experiment actually is
okay
um page 24 it then generates an action
sends it to the environment in an
attempt to make the environment less
surprising could this be translated to a
clinical scenario as follows one I
predict bodily Integrity two I receive
sensory observations disconfirming my
prediction three I generate an action
undergoing treatment to receive sensory
observations that confirm my prediction
of bodily Integrity thereby making my
environment less surprising AKA active
inference
anyone have a thought on that
for qualitative active sounds good let's
just contrast that with other stories
that people could tell
one would be the reward learning story
um I'm rewarded by bodily integrity
I seek out actions that increase my
reward so I decided to go undergo
treatment to increase my reward
active
generative model made a prediction
then based upon sensory observations
policies were selection selected
to reduce surprise there's some
interplay of change your mind and change
the world
the other Story three this is 3A
and then 3B
is
I got the sensory observation
disconfiring my prediction
I updated my prior
now expect
low bodily integrity
issue solved
so
normative in how we describe statistical
problems sure
normative in terms of in the human
clinical environment
suggesting how to act
certainly not
but great start
policies associated with lower expected
free energy G
are assigned a higher probability and
become the policies that an organism
expects to pursue
is this a reason why in a therapeutic
setting change is often so hard to
achieve
because the person often has to select
different policies than they normally do
and these new policies are therefore
assigned lower probability
great question any thought
G
updates the policy prior
so we can look at we're going to come to
this more in chapter five when we start
talking thanks Jay
we're going to talk about it more
um in chapter five
there was a physical human
in case that didn't make any sense
um
we're going to talk about it more in
five
e is the Paul it can be seen as the
policy prior it's
the list of affordances that are
possible
and the number in each of those cells is
How likely those
um are to occur a priori so I turn right
60 of the time I turn left 40 of the
time a priori
if nothing else intervenes I'm going to
continue to replicate that 60 40
behavioral pattern
expected free energy evaluation
sharpens that policy prior into a policy
posterior
that better reflects
expected free energy minimization
as we just discussed which can be
decomposed into the epistemic and
pragmatic value
so
various ways of thinking about it but
certainly in certain settings
if one has a strong habit they have a
precise prior on action
then yes it would be hard to update
because they have a precise prior
on action
but in the end it would come down to the
specific model that you actually make of
that therapeutic setting but again just
qualitatively conversationally
that broadly makes sense
especially if there's a new policy
introduced
one can imagine that it has a low prior
because empirically it's never been seen
like how can one be the kind of person
who runs every day if they haven't
observed themselves doing that
any other comments on that
yeah can I just ask you if there's a
zero prior can it still be updated such
that there is a non-zero posterior
yes that is going to come in
foreign
conjugate prior we were just talking
about it in the chapter seven and that's
what's called learning by Counting
so in that setting you basically like
each time you observe the two options
you drop one ball of that color into an
urn and then your posterior is just
sampling from that urn
so if you have one
um one blue and one green
then the third ball is going to like
update your posterior a lot whereas if
you've got a thousand of each then that
two thousandth and first ball is not
going to update it that much so that's
like more recalcitrant to learning and
then now someone says oh now there are
orange balls
okay I observed an orange ball okay now
we have one orange ball and a thousand
blue and a thousand green
one reason why those models are not like
those models are very situational like
there's no General so answer or or
solution about like adding and also from
a um computational perspective like that
you need to start some of the variables
need to change their dimensionality
and so
currently tools are being developed to
facilitate
specifying and updating the
dimensionality of these models because a
lot of the things that people are just
intuitively curious about are like well
what happens when
somebody gets a piece of information
that helps them realize that a new
affordance is possible and not new
affordance then in the future may or may
not open up another foreign it's like
yeah
cool situation to model
not going to have a general solution at
this point
and last of the pre-stated questions
the 38 they say vfv minimization is the
key outside Loop of active
sufficient to optimize perception of
beliefs about policies
however the notion of policy was
introduced in the context of efe which
is an imagined future thing whereas vfv
is right now
how can beliefs about policies come into
vfv without efe
any thoughts on this
expected free energy is explicitly
calculated
over policies about
um future observations
variational free energy as the question
suggested is about the current status of
the variational distribution
and incoming data
so they're just calculating something
slightly different
um
without efe we simply have energy-based
learning via minimization of vfe
only by calculation of expected free
energy over policy do we get the active
part of active inference yes
expected free energy could be applied at
the one time step
Horizon
um
I'm sure there's other nuances and ways
to address it
but broadly variational free energy is
reactive
in that it's an ongoing unfolding flow
between the generative model and the
incoming data
but it could it can be calculated of
active or passive entities
expected free energy makes a proactive
yeah and vfv the the it could describe
unplanned
reflexive optimal activity
whereas to explicitly consider policy
counterfactuals as such
and evaluate sequences of future
possibilities
only efe has that capacity
okay great great question
um Scott when one model is a candle
flame or pendulum will they only use vfe
yeah so some years ago I'll go for it
first
uh you're just about vfp and
um efe uh well actually
uh efe
includes both uh planning and I mean
action selection planning and also
decision making but uh variation free
energy is uh just about uh I mean it's
not just about planning so efe also
uh includes the action selection or
policy selection and uh of course it's a
requirement for planning and any kind of
decision making but in vfe uh it's just
an uh inference we get by
minimizing that
um
parameter but in the next stage when we
want to act upon that inference we use
efe for the action selection and
decision making and so on
thank you yes
um a few answers on using a candle flame
so here in the strange particles paper
um
thinking about a modeling iterative
process
first we could say we're going to model
it as an inner particle
and then if there's no statistical
variance left to describe
you've done good enough
but you might also need to appeal to a
latent cause like oh it's like it's a
guitar string that's resonating but it's
also like there's like a little gnome
with a circadian rhythm latent Clause
inside
and then it's like the next level of
strange particles like oh this guitar
string is resonating and there's a
circadian gnome
and I think the gnome thinks about what
I'm going to do
but each of those are an empirical
question about what level of
sophistication of cognitive model is
relevant for a given situation
and yes earlier versions before expected
free energy was even introduced
octave was
vse based
and efe was proposed to explicitly
account four counterfactuals in planning
because in the earliest iterations it
was like well we'll just calculate vfv
that's like the real
variable anyway so let's just do vfv on
generative models
and then like just sort of be guided
step by step
and then efe like kind of
ultimately describes and and invokes
variables that vfv doesn't like expected
future observations
foreign
questions
um
just want to quickly
look through
where we're going to go in chapter three
we can of course come back to it for the
coming two weeks but any questions or
thoughts or structuring or notes that
people want to add
um leading up to it of course the more
the better so beginning with a Dawkins
quote about survival machines
chapter 2
was free energy as a means free energy
as a how variational Bayesian inference
as a how
here free energy is going to be
approached from the Y
which is going to be the avoidal of
surprising States
and the ways that that is Manifest
across like self-organized systems and
self-modeling systems
Markov blankets are introduced I'm sure
we'll have a lot of fun discussion so
please all questions that people have on
the topic just write them out you
leverage it by like a hundred thousand
when you actually write it out and
improve others questions because there
are many questions that we have about
these areas
um Markov blankets are defined a certain
way
in a certain way that's carrying less
philosophical baggage than many
initially suspect
the action perception Loops which were
presented as Loops in the previous
chapter
are here presented in what's known as
the particular partition
it's a particular partition because it's
a it's a joke first off it's a specific
way to do it it's not the only way to do
it it's particular
also what it partitions is called a
particle the particle is the blanket and
internal States that's why these are
called interactive conservative and
strange particles the particle is the
generative model of the agent
so the particular partition
helps us operationalize that action
perception Loop scheme
into a more proper Bayesian graph
setting
which enables message passing all these
other things
figure 3.2
is showing a simple example of how
Markov blankets are used in inference
not in some super recursive clinical
setting just in terms of like some
stochastic variables and the ways that
different variables have information
about one another and particularly how
internal and external states can still
contain information about each other
despite being mediated only through the
blanket
3.3 agents with Markov blankets
appear to model the external environment
in the sense that internal States
correspond to a representation of
external states of the system
so there's not like a little thermometer
inside of the head of the generative
model
but there are some statistical patterns
such that we can say that there's Mutual
information between some part of the
temperature and some part of the
generative model
otherwise the agent's actions would be
in sentient with respect to that
environmental variable so that's like
where we get cybernetics good regulator
theorem law of requisite diversity
there's a turn towards
uh or a nod to
some of the Bayesian physics
by Framing the process of surprise
minimization as a hamiltonian principle
of least action we're going to talk
about it more
short summary least action does not mean
most lazy if you shoot a ball out of a
cannon and it follows a parabola that is
the path of least action so least action
does not mean least ATP using it doesn't
mean least carbohydrate burning
doesn't mean smallest computational
model it's a technical physics term
that has a very important meaning and
you'll hear first and others
characterize fep as a principle of least
action for a cognitive systems
3.4 relationship between inference
cognition and stochastic Dynamics
like why are we even talking about
cognition as inference and talking about
all of the statistical stochastic stuff
so here they juxtapose statistical
physics
which has long had an imperative of
minimizing free energy
with Bayesian Infamous inference and
information Theory
which can be mobilized to provide
cognitive interpretations under the
Bayesian brain framework
free energy
again we're not simply talking about ATP
being burnt
it's not Gibbs free energy it's not
calories
but it might have some relationships
3.41 variational free energy model
evidence and surprise
fancy letter surprise as model evidence
we'll come back to it
expected free energy
here we had vfe and surprise real-time
unfolding model evidence as surprise
here's prospective efe and inference to
the most likely trajectory
and 3.5 octave inference a novel
Foundation to understand behavior and
cognition
some summary
of the above
and a little bit of unpacking
about how behavior and cognition are
being unified in active inference
3.6 models policies and trajectories
more discussion about those topics
reconciliation of inactive cybernetic
and predictive theories under octave
inference
those three apparently disconnected
theoretical perspectives are reconciled
in this section according to the authors
and then moving even further active
inference from the emergence of life to
agency is where again in only a several
short paragraphs such as the tip of the
iceberg
there's some discussion of General
um
sentience and agentic properties
of the generative models the kind that
we're modeling with active inference
side box on entropy minimization
yes hardly any maths in chapter three
yeah let's see
um
not in the second half okay equation 3.2
equation 3.1 but both of them are kind
of definitional and surely are described
naturally in the text
definition in the Box three so yes
different style
but it's a breather before chapter four
hits hard again with a math so
thank you all
looking forward to the comments and talk
to you next week